Cloning of a cDNA encoding an importin-alpha and down-regulation of the gene by light in rice leaves 1998 Gene Central Research Institute of Electric Power Industry, Chiba, Japan. The import of nuclear proteins into nuclei begins with recognition of nuclear localization signal-harboring proteins and binding to a nuclear pore targeting complex. A cDNA for an importin-alpha protein, a subunit of the complex, was isolated from rice plants. The amino acid sequence deduced from the nucleotide sequence of the cDNA exhibited a high homology to those of importin-alpha proteins from many organisms such as Arabidopsis thaliana, Saccharomyces cerevisiae, human, mouse, Xenopus laevis and Drosophila melanogaster. Down-regulation of the transcription by light was shown in the leaves of light- and dark-grown seedlings by RNA blot analysis. The down-regulation was specific to leaves, whereas no light effect was observed in root tissues or calli, in which higher levels of the transcript were detected. alpha1a Molecular cloning of a novel importin alpha homologue from rice, by which constitutive photomorphogenic 1 (COP1) nuclear localization signal (NLS)-protein is preferentially nuclear imported 2001 J Biol Chem	National Institute of Agrobiological Resources, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8602, Japan. cjjiang@abr.affrc.go.jp Nuclear import of proteins that contain classical nuclear localization signals (NLS) is initiated by importin alpha, a protein that recognizes and binds to the NLS in the cytoplasm. In this paper, we have cloned a cDNA for a novel importin alpha homologue from rice which is in addition to our previously isolated rice importin alpha1a and alpha2, and we have named it rice importin alpha1b. In vitro binding and nuclear import assays using recombinant importin alpha1b protein demonstrate that rice importin alpha1b functions as a component of the NLS-receptor in plant cells. Analysis of the transcript levels for all three rice importin alpha genes revealed that the genes were not only differentially expressed but that they also responded to dark-adaptation in green leaves. Furthermore, we also show that the COP1 protein bears a bipartite-type NLS and its nuclear import is mediated preferentially by the rice importin alpha1b. These data suggest that each of the different rice importin alpha proteins carry distinct groups of nuclear proteins, such that multiple isoforms of importin alpha contribute to the regulation of plant nuclear protein transport. alpha1a,alpha1b,alpha2 Mutations of genes in synthesis of the carotenoid precursors of ABA lead to pre-harvest sprouting and photo-oxidation in rice 2008 Plant J State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics and National Centre for Plant Gene Research, Beijing 100101, China. Pre-harvest sprouting (PHS) or vivipary in cereals is an important agronomic trait that results in significant economic loss. A considerable number of mutations that cause PHS have been identified in several species. However, relatively few viviparous mutants in rice (Oryza sativa L.) have been reported. To explore the mechanism of PHS in rice, we carried out an extensive genetic screening and identified 12 PHS mutants (phs). Based on their phenotypes, these phs mutants were classified into three groups. Here we characterize in detail one of these groups, which contains mutations in genes encoding major enzymes of the carotenoid biosynthesis pathway, including phytoene desaturase (OsPDS), zeta-carotene desaturase (OsZDS), carotenoid isomerase (OsCRTISO) and lycopene beta-cyclase (beta-OsLCY), which are essential for the biosynthesis of carotenoid precursors of ABA. As expected, the amount of ABA was reduced in all four phs mutants compared with that in the wild type. Chlorophyll fluorescence analysis revealed the occurrence of photoinhibition in the photosystem and decreased capacity for eliminating excess energy by thermal dissipation. The greatly increased activities of reactive oxygen species (ROS) scavenging enzymes, and reduced photosystem (PS) II core proteins CP43, CP47 and D1 in leaves of the Oscrtiso/phs3-1mutant and OsLCY RNAi transgenic rice indicated that photo-oxidative damage occurred in PS II, consistent with the accumulation of ROS in these plants. These results suggest that the impairment of carotenoid biosynthesis causes photo-oxidation and ABA-eficiency phenotypes, of which the latter is a major factor controlling the PHS trait in rice. beta-OsLCY,OsPDS,OsZDS,OsCRTISO|ZEBRA2 A pair of orthologs of a leucine-rich repeat receptor kinase-like disease resistance gene family regulates rice response to raised temperature 2011	BMC Plant Biol National Key Laboratory of Crop Genetic Improvement, National Center of Plant Gene Research (Wuhan), Huazhong Agricultural University, Wuhan 430070, China. BACKGROUND: Rice Xa3/Xa26 disease-resistance gene encodes a leucine-rich repeat (LRR) receptor kinase-type protein against Xanthomonas oryzae pv. oryzae (Xoo) and belongs to a multigene family. However, the functions of most genes in this family are unknown. RESULTS: Here we report that two orthologs of this family, the NRKe from rice variety Nipponbare and 9RKe from variety 93-11 at the RKe locus, have similar functions although they encode different proteins. This pair of orthologs could not mediate resistance to Xoo, but they were transcriptionally induced by raised temperature. Transcriptional activation of NRKe or 9RKe resulted in the formation of temperature-ensitive lesion mimics, which were spots of dead cells associated with accumulation of superoxides, in different organs of the transgenic plants. These plants were more sensitive to high temperature shock than wild-type controls. Transgenic plants carrying a chimeric protein consisting of the LRR domain of NRKe and the kinase domain of Xa3/Xa26 developed the same lesion mimics as the NRKe-transgenic plants, whereas transgenic plants carrying another chimeric protein consisting of the LRR domain of Xa3/Xa26 and the kinase domain of NRKe were free of lesion mimic. All the transgenic plants carrying a chimeric protein were susceptible to Xoo. CONCLUSION: These results suggest that the RKe locus is involved in rice response to raised temperature. The LRR domain of RKe protein appears to be important to sense increased temperature. The RKe involved temperature-related pathway and Xa3/Xa26-mediated disease-resistance pathway may partially overlap. RKe,Xa26|Xa3.